<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods interest in the King set forth in a sermon preached in the cathedral of Edinburgh October the 14th at the anniversary commemoration of His Majesties birth / by one of the ministers of the city.</title>
            <author>Mackqueen, John, d. 1734.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51016</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M226</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16980</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13370252</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13370252</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99305</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51016)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99305)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 465:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods interest in the King set forth in a sermon preached in the cathedral of Edinburgh October the 14th at the anniversary commemoration of His Majesties birth / by one of the ministers of the city.</title>
                  <author>Mackqueen, John, d. 1734.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nath. Thompson ... and sold by Alexander Ogston ... at Edingurgh,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: John Mackqueene.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms II, 62 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons --  Scotland --  17th century --  2 rbgenr.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99305:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99305:1"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable JAMES Earl of <hi>Perth,</hi> Lord <hi>Drummond</hi> and <hi>Stobhall,</hi> &amp;c. Lord High Chancellor of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> AND JOHN Earl of <hi>Mellfort,</hi> Viſcount of <hi>Forth,</hi> &amp;c. Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Secretary of State for the ſaid Kingdom; Knights of the moſt Noble and moſt Ancient Order of the THISTLE: AND Of His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy-Councel, in both Kingdoms of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhips,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Illuſtrious Character, you deſervedly bear, is no leſs demonſtration of the King's profound Judgment, and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to His People, than marks of Honour to your
<pb facs="tcp:99305:2"/>Family, or Favour to your Perſons. It is the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of the Nation, as the King makes no Impreſs but on the fineſt Metals, no more does he imploy Miniſters, but ſuch whoſe intrinſick Worth juſtifies His prudent Choice, and Endears Him to His People: We find by your faithful Management of the great Truſt you have, that State Miniſters are not now, as in ſome former Ages, Screens to the Prince, to keep off the popular Hatred of thoſe Diſcontented at the Government: But rather like thoſe reflective Glaſſes, which, by intercepting the Love of His People, double the ſame towards the Sovereign. The Intereſt your Fidelity to the King's Concerns has given you in his Majesties good Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, you have Improven to the King's Mind, for the Happineſs of His Subjects: The Boldneſs with which you aſſert his Right, the preſence of Mind with which you unfold the well-mean'd Overtures, but not ſo Happy, of others: The dexterity by which you manage your better laid Propoſals; the unbyaſſedneſs of your Temper, which no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration can induce to wreſt Juſtice; the Zeal wherewith you encourage the Loyal, and diſhearten the Factious; the Humanity, wherewith you receive Addreſſes from all, without reſpect of Perſons, has a very auſpicious Influence on the whole Nation, to confirm it in its Duty to the King, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Government.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99305:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Virtuous and excellent Peſons, as they are more eaſily Exalted, and that with more Honour to the Prince, leſs Envy to the Court, and Grumbling to the People; ſo they prove more Faithful to their Truſt, more Grateful to the King the Fountain of their Advancement, more Serviceable to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, more Acceptable to both God and Man: Hence it is, the great Figure you make in our <hi>Horizon</hi> is ſo little ſpoken againſt; Although the Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch Dignities in two Brethren at one time, has as rare Preſidents in our <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> as there are in them Examples of ſuch a Conſtellation of Virtues, or the preſent Age affords Inſtances of ſuch ſingular Accompliſhments.</p>
            <p>He who knows and conſiders,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>K.</hi> Rob. <hi>III. Married to</hi> Arabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, <hi>Daughter to Sir</hi> John Drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond <hi>of</hi> Stobhall; <hi>She was Mother to K.</hi> James <hi>I.</hi>
               </note> how congenial Loyalty muſt needs be to your Noble Family, which has the Honour to be ſo early ally'd to the Crown, will leſs wonder yet at the benign Influences of the Throne, towards Perſons, whoſe Integrity to the King, is not only conveyed with Their blood in a long Series of worthy Progenitors, but is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of Conſcience and ſenſe of Duty: Yet do not I think, it was the Advantage of your Quality and Blood, ſo much as the Eminence of your Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments has attracted the Kings Good Will towards you: His Majeſty, as an Angel of God, diſcerns where Heaven qualifies and prepares fit Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for his purpoſe and his Peoples Weal: And,
<pb facs="tcp:99305:3"/>as an obſervant Vicegerent, He ſeconds the more Curious Ingravings of the Divine Hand with ſome Strokes of his own: And where theſe concur in State-Miniſters, the Kingdom is more Happy, than when according to <hi>Plato</hi>'s Model, <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers govern, or Governours aim to be ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is no ſmall Joy and Satisfaction to all honeſt Hearts, and it has wonderfully reviv'd the Spirits of the Loyal in the Nation; to ſee the Favour of the Court run in ſo right a Chanel towards per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of ſuch untainted Loyalty, Ability and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, who are no more united in Blood than in Noble Deſigns, for the Honour of the King, the Security of his People, and the Intereſt of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: No ſmall Prognoſtick of perpetuating our Happineſs under ſo Wiſe, ſo Gallant a Prince, and ſuch Excellent Miniſters.</p>
            <p>We now ſee theſe Happy Days, in which the Kings Favour is not made mercenary, nor due Rewards of Loyalty miſ-plac'd on Intriguers with Faction: and that none can obtain them, but by his Fidelity, or retain them but by perſeverance in his Duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lords,</hi> It may be thought ſtrange, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how zealous a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> I am, I ſhould have made bold to implore your Patronage, and perchance there will not be wanting ſome, who will whiſper againſt it: But I dare openly own, what
<pb facs="tcp:99305:3"/>they dare but privately condemn, as no difference of Religion can alienate my affection and duty from my Prince; no more will it make me omit my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to His Miniſters, regard to their Authority, or obedience to their Command; my zeal for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion will not raſe the eſteem I have for Worth and Virtue, ſo eminently ſet: And where could I dedicate a Diſcourſe better, than to ſuch conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous inſtances and promoters of it? I once enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd the Vanity to have addreſſed it to His Sacred Majeſty, whoſe Title to the productions of our Brains is no leſs, than to thoſe of our Loyns and Fortunes; But conſidering Princes are not to be rudely accoſted by mean Perſons, but to be approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with profound Reverence by the Mediation of others, I have preſumed to publiſh this firſt Eſſay under your Honourable Names, which if it be ſo happy as to touch the Kings hands, or get a glance of his eye, I am more rewarded than I could expect, or can deſerve. I remember an expreſſion of that Prodigy of Piety, Conſtancy, and Eloquence, King <hi>Charles I.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Scrini Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra.</note> in a Letter to the Univerſity of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> approving their Election of the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> for their <hi>Chancellor,</hi> upon His Majeſties Recommendation, He ſays, <hi>We ſhall ever conceive, that an Honour done to a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon VVe Favour, is out of a Royal Reſpect had to Our Self:</hi> As my reſpect to the King put
<pb facs="tcp:99305:4"/>me on this Service, ſo it has induced me to this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, upon which account it is only acceptable to your Lordſhips, who make Perſons affection to to the King the meaſure of your favour towards them: By which the World ſees, the Kings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns go nearer you than your own; to promote which, as there are none more ſincerely ſet than you are, ſo there is none more cordially Prayes, you may Live long for his Majeſties Service, for the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of your Families, and the Happineſs of the Nation, than</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Moſt Faithful, Moſt Humble, And moſt Devoted Servant. JOHN MACKGUEENE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99305:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm 2.62.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Yet have I ſet my King upon my holy Hill of <hi>Zion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SOme <hi>Virtuoſo</hi>'s of the <hi>Heathen</hi> World, who were puzzl'd at the unequal diſtribution of Things, reſolv'd the events of this Life into meer Chance, or a Fortuitous concourſe of ſecond Cauſes: Others of them more Studious, and ſo more refin'd, attributed the good or bad ſucceſs of Human Affairs, to the ſwinge of a fatal neceſſity; ſome look'd no higher than to the Will, Conduct, Liberty and Wiſdom of Man, as the great diſpoſer of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns: But thoſe of greater perſpicacy, and more ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated reaſon, referred the accompliſhments or fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mens Deſigns to a higher Hand,
<note place="margin">Natura, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Fortuna Caſus, omnia unius ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Dei no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina.</note> even Divine Providence, which they meant under the various ſhapes and Names, the Vanity of ſome, the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of others, or the Superſtition of a third Party gave it: And we, who have a more ſure word of Prophecy, a clearer Light, and a ſurer guide, revere as the ſole Arbitrator of the Emergencies and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of this World, that ſuperintends all our Actions and Contrivances, ſometimes proſpering the moſt unlikely, ſometimes defeating the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing, attempts, even thoſe which have wind and tide, (ſo to ſpeak) a concatenation of all neceſſary Cauſes, a concurrence of all probable Circumſtances, to make them Auſpicious, and Crown them with ſucceſsful Iſſues: To convince us all,
<note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 10.23.</note> 
               <hi>That the way
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99305:5"/>of man is not in himſelf, that it is not in him to direct his ſteps.</hi> And though Man propoſeth, yet it is God diſpoſeth, a clear inſtance of which, we have in this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and more particularly in our Text, <hi>Yet have I ſet,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Pſalm,</hi> as many others, repreſents to us myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally the Succeſs of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Kingdom, and the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Throne, maugre all the oppoſition of Men and Devils; but literally <hi>David</hi>'s eſtabliſhment in his Regal Office, and Royalty; after all his Troubles, in deſpight of all the Difficulties which lay in his way; and how fitly applyable to our <hi>Sovereign</hi>'s advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will anon appear.</p>
            <p>I will at this occaſion confine my ſelf to the Literal Importance of the Text, and conſider from it: <hi>Firſt,</hi> The peculiar Intereſt God claimes to himſelf in the Setlement of Kingly Government. <hi>I have ſet my King. Secondly,</hi> The Wiſe and Powerful Conduct of Divine Providence in making good his ſpecial Care of Kings, and bringing about their Settlement, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Rage and Malice, the Power and Plots of Enemies, whether the Contrivances, Wits, or Conſpiracies of Grandees: Whether the Fury of an Heady Multitude, or vain Madneſs of Popular Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; all which is expreſs'd, or couch'd in the preced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Verſes, recapitulated and wrapt in this ſhort ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſative Particle, <hi>Yet;</hi> Which how ſmall ſoever it appear to you, is very Emphatick: The Filings of Gold are precious, and ſo are the leaſt Expreſſions of Divine Writ: As we hang great weights on ſmall Pins, and ſet large Wheels on work by little Springs, ſo, much is included in this ſmall Syllable <hi>Yet;</hi> That is, <hi>Maugre all the rage of the</hi> Heathen, <hi>and the vain Imagination of the People, in deſpight of the Power of Adverſary Princes, and the Policy of Rulers: I
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99305:5"/>have accompliſh'd my Purpoſe, and conſummated my Work,</hi> Yet have I ſet my King, <hi>&amp;c. I have laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at their cloſe-lay'd Projects, and derided their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, I have blaſted their Attempts with the breath of my wrath: I have quell'd their force, and broken their Bands; I have maſter'd their Power, and daunted their Courage, and own'd my Anointed: And inſtead of their breaking our Bands, or caſting away our Cords, I have broken them with an Iron Mace, and cruſh'd them as a Potter's Veſſel;</hi> So much is imported in this Yet, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Firſt,</hi> The peculiar concern God takes for Kingly Government: The general Providence of God is conſpicuous in the Order and Variety, the Beauty and Harmony, the Diverſity, yet Uniformity, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in the frame of Nature: The Univerſe is no greater Monument of his Power, than 'tis a Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of his Providence: But his ſpecial Providence ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalizes it ſelf in the Care of Kings, and Fate of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; in diſpoſal of Crowns, and conferring of Scepters, in the mighty Revolutions of Government: As it is a great Diminution of the Reverence we owe the Deity, to aſcribe every petty Chance, every trifling Emergent to a ſpecial Surveyance; ſo not to range the Momentous tranſactions of the Lives of publick Perſons under his peculiar Inſpection, not to attribute the ſignal Benedictions of Nations to his Conduct, is Prophaneneſs or a piece of Preſumptuous negligence. Well then may God claim a peculiar Intereſt in the eſtabliſhment of Regal Authority ſo beneficial to Mankind, and advantagious to Chriſtian Society. Kings are the chiefeſt Objects of Gods choiceſt Care, whom he tenders with more than ordinary Affection; <hi>It is he that advances them to their Thrones and eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhes them thereon:</hi> This appears,
<note place="margin">Dan. 2.21. <hi>and</hi> 37. verſ.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:99305:6"/>
            <p n="1">1.
<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 8.5.</note> From the Divine Inſtitution of this kind of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, God ſays, <hi>By me Kings reigne, and Princes decree Juſtice:</hi> Whatever <hi>Phanaticks</hi> or <hi>Republicans</hi> ſay, Kings derive their Authority from a higher Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain than the People, they have their Commiſſion from Heaven, are God's Delegates, and Vice-gerents, not the Creatures of the multitude: And as <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> hath its Original from God, who ſettled this Model amongſt his own peculiar People; ſo it carries more lively Veſtigies of his Government of the World, than any other: Hence it is God communicates his Name, as well as Power to
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 82 6.</note> Kings:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cujus juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu &amp; homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes naſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, hujus juſſu &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur apti iis qui ab ipſis regnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> lib. 5. cir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a finem.</note> 
               <hi>Iraeneus</hi> tells, <hi>Kings are conſtituted by the very ſame Authority and Command, by which Men are made and born, for the benefit of them over whom they exerciſe Juriſdiction:</hi> Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is no human Invention, for modelling the World into Order, no politick Contrivance for Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplining mankind into Society: Much-lefs, an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to gratify the Ambition of any who would va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour it in Pomp and Splendor: No, its Pedigree may be traced higher; it brings its extraction from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and the ſtate of Innocency will not exclude it.</p>
            <p>The general cuſtom of Nations in owning and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining this form, ſpeaks out its Divinity, and the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Intereſt of Providence in maintaining it; even theſe Nations, that are not more diſtant from others in Situation, than they are different in Manners; how wild ſoever the Soil be, without Culture; how Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage the People, without Arts, are yet under <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical</hi> Government: This
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Omni autem in re conſenſio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mnium gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium lex na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura putanda eſt</hi> Cicero.</note> Univerſal Harmony is no ſmall Teſtimony to its Divinity; it muſt be ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Beauty that conquers all Hearts, and ſets it Trophies every where; which not only the beſt Poliſh'd and Civiliz'd Nations in the World, but even Barbarous <hi>Scythians,</hi> rude <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricans</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99305:6"/>and Wild <hi>Indians</hi> are enamour'd with: It muſt be Heavenly <hi>Manna</hi> that can ſatisfy every Palate, conſidering the contrary Tempers and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Diſpoſitions of Men. It muſt needs be more than Human, that is rever'd in the dark Corners of <hi>America,</hi> as well as in the refin'd parts of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The peculiar Intereſt of Providence in reference to Kingly Government, may be demonſtrated from the <hi>Proviſo</hi>'s ſcatter'd up and down his World, for the Security of thoſe entruſted therewith: By which we ſee the Spirit of God ſtrangely ſuper-intends the Cauſe of Kings; <hi>Moſes</hi> layes a Bridle on our Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues,
<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 22.28.</note> 
               <hi>That we ſpeak no Evil againſt them;
<note n="*" place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.20.</note> Solomon</hi> will dive deeper, and not ſo much as allow an <hi>Evil Thought, not a Whiſper or a Mutter, though in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creteſt receſs of our Dwellings:</hi> The <hi>Goſpel</hi> is no leſs friendly, St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Jude</hi> go further, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude an inward Deſpection of them <hi>Criminous;</hi> ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if they would have the Tongue curb'd from ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Mouth from muttering, the Mind from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Diſloyalty: They would not have the Hands lift up againſt them in Cruelty and Blood: <hi>Jeremiah</hi> commands the <hi>Jews</hi> to pray for the Life of the King of <hi>Babylon:</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts Supplications to be made for <hi>Nero:</hi> Is it likely, they would allow their Subjects to petition them in Tumults, to ſtarve them by Votes of Precluſion, to conſpire againſt their Perſons, or bandy againſt their Authority, to Invade their Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories with force, and dye Scaffolds with their Blood: No, no, it would extreamly detract from the Divine Wiſdom, to eſtabliſh a Polity, and make ſuch Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionary Laws for its Safety, and then approve the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Fetches by which ſome <hi>Demagogues</hi> would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine it, or the open Force by which ſome Saucy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99305:7"/>Encroachers would invade it: This were to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-act his own Ordinance, and to reſemble <hi>Charles</hi> the V. his Diſingenuity, who commanded Publick Prayers to be made for <hi>Clement</hi> the VII throughout all his Dominions; when by his Authority his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains held him Incarcerated.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Preſervation of this Model in the World, from its beginning to this very time, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all the attempts of men to break it, or ſhake it off; is no ſmall indication of God's peculiar concern for it:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Abſiſtens a Deo homo in tantum effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit ut in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni inquietu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine et homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid vel avae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritia verſare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> Iraene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as lib. 5. cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a finem.</note> He that conſiders, how that ſince <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s Fall (who was the firſt Rebel and Incendiary, let factious <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> and feditious Boutefeaves glory if they can in their common Father,) and <hi>Adam</hi>'s Miſcarriage, the whole race of Mankind became Turbulent and Ungovernable: How Contentious are ſome, and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious are others: How Diſcontented are ſome, and cunningly Seditious are others, to work on their Tempers: He that conſiders the Inconſtancy of the Populacy, the envy of Powerful Competitors; the Conſpiracies of Grandees; the Jealouſy of ſome State-Miniſters among themſelves, and their Treachery to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Sovereign:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſt in omni populo quid malignum &amp; qu rulum in Imperantes.</hi> Tacitus.</note> The Skittiſhneſs of People, and the Natural Untowardneſs that is generally in Men againſt their Governours: That notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this, <hi>Monarchy</hi> ſhould keep footing in the World: We may conclude, there is more than an ordinary Providence in it, and ſay in an Extaſie, <hi>It is the Lord's doing, and is marvellous in our Eyes: It is he that giveth Salvation to Kings, and the Shields of the Earth belong unto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſpecial concern of providence in behalf of Kings, appears in the ſad and deplorable end of thoſe, who either by open Violence, or ſecret Treachery, invade their Authority, or diſturb their Government:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99305:7"/>God will not ſuffer ſuch violations of his Ordinance to eſcape ſignal tokens of his diſpleaſure; nor have there been any ſinners more remarkable inſtances of divine vengeance, nor human juſtice, than ſuch; witneſs <hi>Corah,</hi> and his Confederates; <hi>Abſolom,</hi> and <hi>Achitophel; Zimri,</hi> and <hi>Joab; Sheba,</hi> and <hi>Amaſa;</hi> our own Chronicles and Times afford freſh bleeding Examples, of the calamitous fall of ſome Families, once illuſtrious, but now levell'd with the ground, with ignominy, and diſgrace, as the juſt reward of their unjuſt aſpiring, and rebellious oppoſing the Regal Authority,
<note place="margin">Jude 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>theſe periſhed in the gain-ſaying of Core:</hi> Let all Rebells and Seditious Perſons be afraid, ſince they trace the ſteps, they'l taſt the puniſhment of ſuch Criminals; Sedition is as odious now as ever, and the Divine Providence as ready to detect, and cruſh it, as ever.</p>
            <p>I will not entertain you with a politick Lecture on Goverment, this is not my province; nor will I ſo far diſparage Monarchy, as to make any Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons betwixt it and any other Form, being fully aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no other Model has ſuch a ſtamp of Divine Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, a King being the cleareſt reflection of the Deity upon Earth; nor will I adduce theſe irrefra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable teſtimonies from the Hero's of the Church, who determined for Kingly Government, in an Age they were ſhatter'd with its frowns, more than che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed with its ſmiles, and felt its Proſecution more than Protection; nor will I heap up thoſe Elogies, with which the great Maſters of human policy have raiſed it, beyond all ſaucy competition of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Models; only mind you of a pretty ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of one of the Glories of his Age, the great <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> who ſpeaking of the neceſſity of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and how Rulers are the Vice-gerents and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99305:8"/>lively pictures of God; he ſays, ordinary Magiſtrates are a contracted Character of God, or his Picture drawn to the neck and ſhoulders; theſe above them were his Picture drawn to the middle, but the King was his Portraiture in full length: And for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Monarchy, i'le aſſert, it is the moſt Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, the moſt honourable, the moſt advantagious to the ends of Government, and happineſs of Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Kingly-Government is the moſt ancient, even as old as the World, and in deſpight of all the haters of it, with it, and no ſooner ſhall it receive its Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; though it may be rationally conceived, the World is near its diſſolution, when ſo conſiderable a Pillar of its ſtanding, is ſo barbarouſly attacked, and rudely inveyed againſt, by the enemies of all Order; indeed things that fortuitouſly ſtart up by the policy of ſome Ages, or the cuſtom of particular Nations, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire not that Univerſal Reputation, or perpetual continuance, wherewith Monarchy has, and is like to keep footing in the World.
<note place="margin">Cortum eſt, omnes anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quas gentes regibus puru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe. Cicero.</note> It is beyond all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, all Nations, any way famed for Antiquity, were in ſubjection to Kingly-Government, the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation was laid in <hi>Adam,</hi> nor did it expire with him, but was entailed on his Eldeſt Son, who, though ſhort of his Brother <hi>Abel</hi> in piety, yet did not loſe his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority over him, for it is ſaid, <hi>his deſire ſhall be to thee, and thou ſhalt rule over him.</hi> Dominion was not early founded in Grace, according to the whimſey's of the <hi>Fifth-Monarchy-Men.</hi> It is certain, a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth without a King is the natural offspring of Ambition, and the product of a teeming Faction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Kingly-Government is the moſt honourable; bleſſed art thou,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.8.</note> O Land, when thy King is the Son of Nobles; upon this ſcore we may vie with all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99305:8"/>in the World, none of them can boaſt ſuch a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Princes, ſuch a Lineal Succeſſion of Kings, in a regular and orderly Deſcent; what interruption of the Monarchy, what bandying of the Scepter into diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Families, without Allyance and Blood intereſt betwixt them, to the greivous convulſion of the Eſtate moſt Kingdoms in <hi>Europe</hi> have undergone, How ſhort-liv'd has the Royal Power been in ſome Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, like a glazing Meteor or blazing Comet, whilſt Ours, by the Divine Bleſſing, has been a fixed Star, or like the Sun, rather caſting the benign influences, to the Elevation of our Nobility, the Cheriſhing of our Clergy, the Eſtabliſhment of our Gentry, the Protection of our Commons? We admire a ſtately Palace for the orderly variety of its parts, and the beauty of its ſtructure, but we ſo much the more regard and commend it, that it has ſtood out againſt wind and weather, and the injury of time, ſo many Ages. And certainly, ſince a ſpecial providence has through ſo many ſucceſſive Generations ſignaliz'd its care of our Monarchy, to the envy of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and aſtoniſhment of our Enemies, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Crown in its Right and Lineal Courſe, to His Head, who now carries it, (who though it were not by inheritance, as it is indiſputable, yet were it by merit His Right to wear it,) we may expect no common or ordinary Bleſſings, from One, to whom the Virtues of thoſe Princely <hi>Hero</hi>'s, are convey'd with their blood.</p>
            <p>You of the Nobility, my Illuſtrious Hearers, may be encouraged here-from, to Submiſſion and Loyalty; You ſerve a King who is the Son of Nobles, who was Born to command you, and from his very Cradle has an Air of Greatneſs; <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſays, there is a certain Greatneſs, and innate Gallantry
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99305:9"/>of Spirit,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Plut.</note> in thoſe Deſcended of worthy Progenitors; ſuch have ſpirit and courage for Heroick Atchievments, whilſt theſe <hi>Terrae Filii,</hi> theſe of obſcure exſtraction, have a great deal of Copper or Droſs mixed with their Ore or Argent, are by Nature deſtin'd to low or ſordid Imploys: You ſerve no upſtart of the Rabble, or creature of the Populace, nor a King by chance, but one who hath all the Majeſty of a Prince, and the Gallantry of a Hero. It was the favour of His Predeceſſors, diſtinguiſhed yours from their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, the Dignity of the Subject being a Ray from the Sovereign, as His is a Beam of the Divinity. How can you look on your ſelves, and theſe Badges of His favour, by which you are Elevated above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and not reflect Honour to the Original of your Grandeur? you ſhould conſider, that as the Painter conſulted beſt for perpetuating his memory, when he indented his own Image in <hi>Minerva</hi>'s Picture, that the one could not be eraſed without defacing the other. There is ſuch an Union betwixt His Majeſty and you, that an injury done him reflects as much diſhonour as Ingratitude on your ſelves, and the more the Sovereignty is depreſſed, the more you will ever be trampled upon; ſo that it is an equal wonder, a Noble-man ſhould ever be a Traitor, as a Son be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Parricide, or a Wife Murther her Husband.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Kingly Government is moſt accommodated for the ſafety of the Subject,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Polyb.</note> and the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Peace and Proſperity in a Nation; the great Bulwark of a Kingdoms Felicity, are in <hi>Polybius</hi>'s Opinion, Concord at home, and Strength againſt Foreign Invaſion: <hi>Monarchy</hi> prevents the Emulations and Claſhings of Subjects for Priority and Power; and ſo ſecures the State from Civil Commotions:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99305:9"/>And by uniting the Subjectsunder one common Head, it provides beſt againſt Foreign Encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>We our ſelves know, that the ſhort Miſ-rule of our late <hi>Demagogues</hi> produced more miſchief to their Nation, than the worſt of our <hi>Monarchs</hi> ever did, when they moſt out-ſtretch'd their Power: And there are rare Inſtances upon Record of any of our Lawful Sovereigns, whoſe Miſcarriages were not more than pre-ponderated by the Advantages of their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Neither <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> which is but the Grandees bandying into a Faction; or <hi>Democracy,</hi> which is a confus'd Popularity rank'd into a <hi>Sham-Order,</hi> can ever make the Subjects ſo Unite at Home, or ſo For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable to their Neighbours as <hi>Monarchy</hi> will make them; upon which account we may ſafely and firmly conclude, it is beſt accommodated for the Honour and Strength, for the Safety and Proſperity of a People.</p>
            <p>And were it not ſo, the Divine Providence, which diſpoſes all things by the higheſt Wiſdom, exacteſt Reaſon, and profoundeſt Juſtice, would not ſo ſignal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly own it; and this leads me naturally to the ſecond Head: And that is, the Myſterious, Wonderful and Powerful conduct of Providence, in making good his ſpecial Care of Kings, and bringing about their Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, notwithſtanding all oppoſition to the contrary; all which is included in this adverſative Particle, <hi>Yet will I ſet my King,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I ſee Almighty God, not only Accompliſhes his Work, but Magnifies and Extols the ſame; takes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency in viewing the Parts, in recounting the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Circumſtances that may enhance the ſame: That it may become at once the Object of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies wonder, and of his own rejoycing; of their Shame, and his Glory: Here in a Holy Triumph, he boaſts
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99305:10"/>that maugre all the rage of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> maugre all the Power of the Kings of the World, the Policy of the Rulers of the Earth; the Combination of their Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates, maugre all their Craft, and Cruelty, maugre their Spight and Strength, he did his work, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Indeed the Divine Providence is conſpicuouſly Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant in baffling the Attempts, and conquering the Enemies of Kingly Government, <hi>Yet have I ſet,</hi> &amp;c. The Rage and Plots of Gods Adverſaries are Illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating Shades to the Honour of the Victory; and the Glory of the Conqueſt, he obtains in behalf of his Anointed: O! the Myſterious Conduct of Divine Providence, which ſports with the Strength, laughs at the Spight, makes a game of the Policy, and a paſtime of the Power of poor Mortals; when levell'd againſt his Purpoſe, and over-rules their Counſels and Actings, to further what they intended to defeat: The Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God never appears with greater Luſtre, his Oeconomy is never more wonderful, than in Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the means of cruſhing, into occaſions of more ſignal conſummating his Work; as here, this magnifies his Wiſdom, and exalts his Power, that he may well, like a triumphant Conqueror, brave it over his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd Foes, or like as a Mariner (ſolaced with the after reflections on the paſt dangers of his tedious Voyage,) ſits down and exults at the whiſtling of the Wind and the noiſe of the Waves, when his Ship is ſecurely Harbour'd, and he himſelf paſt danger, <hi>Yet have I ſet,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is our Kings <hi>Birth-day,</hi> and I know nothing more ſuitable to this days Solemnity, or the Text, than a few Reflections on ſome Circumſtances rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his Advancement to the <hi>Throne</hi> of His An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, which may raiſe our eſteem of Gods Wiſdom,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99305:10"/>and beget ſome Joy and Satisfaction in Us; in the ſurvey of the Conduct of his Providence in ſubduing his Foes, we are not only truly Thankful enough, except we expand our Thoughts, and ſtretch our Fancy to contemplate the ſeveral Methods, by which the <hi>Factious</hi> Party ſought to Juſtle Him from His Right: The viewing theſe in their juſt Dimenſions, may conduce to the further Magnifying the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and admiring the Righteouſneſs of God.</p>
            <p>God ſhould not loſe his Honour, by omitting any remarkable Paſſage, or by a careleſs touch or ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial mentioning of theſe Stratagems, whereby they ſought to croſs his Providence, or fruſtrate his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, in the Oppoſition they made againſt the <hi>King:</hi> And that the Conduct of Providence may appear in its Beauty; let us take a view of thoſe Difficulties which ſeem'd to obſtruct; of theſe Intricacies which way laid; theſe Mountains of Oppoſition which withſtood, theſe Intrigues and Croſs actings which were like to Baffle our Soveraign's Aſcent to the <hi>Throne;</hi> let me rip up the various Scenes of the reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Faction,</hi> by which they ſought, and thought to ſtop His Paſſage thereto.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ordinary Prologue to all Miſchief, the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brio</hi> of <hi>Sedition,</hi> the <hi>Cockatrice</hi> Egg of <hi>Rebellion;</hi> repining Complaints, malicious Murmurings, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented Whiſpers; loaden with which, Deſigning Men ſent to the ſeveral Corners of the Nation, to alienate their Hearts from the King, that Then, and now is; and diſpoſe them to take Fire againſt a fit op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for the common Cumbuſtion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. The <hi>Devil,</hi> who himſelf was the firſt Rebel, inſpires his Followers with cunning, and ſlight enough to manage his Treaſonable <hi>Intrigues</hi> againſt <hi>Kings:</hi> And theſe Helliſh Inſtruments vent Speeches of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99305:11"/>Conſtruction, that like their Maſters Reſponſes may be interpreted either to good or evil Purpoſes in promiſcuous Companies: They make ſuch Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations againſt the Government, with <hi>Ifs</hi> and <hi>Ands,</hi> with <hi>Winks</hi> and <hi>Nods,</hi> and a thouſand <hi>Grimaces,</hi> with <hi>Sighs</hi> and <hi>Sobs,</hi> that ſome well-meaning People are wheedled to think Them the only Patriots, the beſt Repairers of our Breaches, the fitteſt Redreſſers of our Grievances, and Reformers of our Diſorders; If a Happy juncture of Affairs could promote ſuch to bear ſway:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In ſerendo querelas &amp; ambiguos de</hi> Galba <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones,</hi> Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</note> Thus <hi>Otho</hi> by his ſligh Hits at <hi>Galba,</hi> and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous Expreſſions concerning him, paved the way to his ruine: O! the pious Regrets, the heavy Sighs, the mournful Complaints theſe <hi>Hypocrites</hi> have belch'd out, with lifted-up Eyes and Hands, with mortify'd Looks, but Cruel Hearts for the Oppreſſions of the Land: And when they have made Tryal of Peoples Tempers, and diſpoſed ſome by this previous Art to be of their Party, they advance a ſtep further.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe hollow Blaſts and ſecret Whiſpers bluſter out in ſcurrilous Libels, peſtiferous Pamphlets, and licentious Invectives; whereby the King is Traduc'd, His Miniſters Defam'd, His Government Aſpers'd; Theſe are the little Beagles, the Cruel Hunters, the Ring-leaders of the Party, heat and ply the great Beaſt of many Heads, and few Eyes, and little Brains, (the Populacy with,) before they let go their great Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds, or appear with Cannons in the Field: Theſe are light Fore-runners of Fatal Conſpiracies and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Events, the ordinary Premiſes of <hi>Rebellion:</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Incendiaries will ever find or fancy Matter for Quarrel in the beſt modell'd Government upon Earth: Theſe who make bold with the <hi>Kings</hi> Name, will not ſpare his Perſon, if a concurrence of advantagious Circumſtances fall in to ſecond their Helliſh pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99305:11"/>When People are ſhaken from that Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the <hi>King</hi>'s Name and Perſon, which is no leſs the Bulwark of their Safety, than it is the Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of the Sovereign's Dignity; there is an open door to all Inſolent Invaſions on his Authority: The <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> knowing the Empire our <hi>Monarchs</hi> have in the Hearts of their People, (beyond any other <hi>Kings</hi> in the World) have ever labour'd by Reproaches and Calumnies to Alienate their Affections from them: This is indeed no new Stratagem of the Party; for as our Saviour ſays, <hi>So Perſecuted they the Prophets that were before you:</hi> So Maligned they with their Libels and virulent Tongues the former <hi>Kings;</hi> ſo did they Slander their Miniſters of State, Miſ-repreſenting their Actings, and Plotted againſt their Lives.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is a Damn'd Conſpiracy under the Flag of a <hi>Sham-Popiſh-Plot,</hi> ſet on foot, and carried on with ſuch Helliſh Artifice, as blinded the Wiſdom of the Nation: And the Leaders of the <hi>Faction</hi> in this out-did their Predeceſſors, who ſeem'd to have been but Puny-Pioneers for undermining the Government, in compariſon of theſe <hi>Engineers:</hi> How far the <hi>King</hi> was Impos'd upon, and his <hi>Parliaments</hi> deluded, the Iſſue (in the ſad Executions, which if continu'd, had exhauſted ſome of the Innocent and beſt Blood of the Nation,) has left upon Record: And if the Wiſdom and Courage of his preſent Majeſty had not a wak'ned the <hi>King,</hi> and the Honeſt of the Land to look about them, and detected the Cheat; We had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd before we had apprehended any Danger: It is an old Remark,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quibus de conjuratione comperta non creditur niſi occiſis.</hi> Livius.</note> 
               <hi>Conſpiracies againſt the King and Government are not believ'd till perpetrated:</hi> One of the neateſt <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> of our Nation, has this Politick Reflection on the Conſpiracy againſt King <hi>James</hi> I. Which the Univerſal Benignity of his Nature, being
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99305:12"/>one of the moſt Accompliſh'd Princes, and beſt Lov'd by his People in the World, would not ſuffer his Councel to believe any durſt have attempted againſt ſo good a Monarch, though yet he periſh'd by it: He ſays,
<note place="margin">Will. Drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> James 1.</note> 
               <hi>People believe not any Conjure againſt his Prince, till they find the Treaſon take effect; and diſtruſt the Plot till they ſee him Dead: But the Death of ſuch who are ſuſpected to be Authors of Diſorders in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, ſpares an infinite number of Lives, and much Civil Blood, when they are firſt ſurpriz'd; neither are too ſtrict Circumſtances of Law to be obſerv'd, when a ſmall delay may aboliſh all obſerving of Order and Laws:</hi> And indeed too much caution is needleſs, where ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity requires ſpeed; dilatory Methods againſt Traytors has diminiſh'd the Authority of the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> and given too much time to its Implacable Enemies, to gather ſtrength, and make head againſt it, to its diſſolution.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Sedition</hi> peeps out through the crevis of <hi>Pamphlets</hi> and <hi>Libels,</hi> or ſhews its Horns in <hi>Tumults,</hi> it is in its Infancy, and may be ſuppreſs'd with leſs expence of Blood and Money: But if it be permitted to commence to its full ſtature, and break out in a Monſtrous <hi>Rebellion,</hi> the Actors are Burnt with the Flames of their own kindling, and Severity againſt the Ring-leaders, is the Security of the <hi>Throne,</hi> and the Safety of the <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Party becoming bold, if not impudent with their Succeſs, they'll ſcorn to deliver their Mind in Slie-inſinuations, or ambiguous Phraſes: They'll pull off the Mask, they'll quarrel at the <hi>Kings</hi> Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, limit and curtail it by Votes, Exclude the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Heir, and Starve the <hi>King</hi> by diſcharging any to ſupply Him by Loan, or advance on His own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue; A Cruelty the meaneſt of the Nation would
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99305:12"/>have juſtly counted intolerable; we may rationally enough conclude, theſe, who would have famiſhed the King, would have cut his Throat if they could; and theſe, who would not permit him to improve His own, would never help him with theirs in his extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. God knows, if the King were of ſuch Mens Dyeting, how ſlender would His Fare prove, how nigardly His Commons, and ſorry His Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? He would have been little better than another <hi>Lazarus</hi> at the Gates of theſe <hi>Diveſes,</hi> only with this diſſimilitude, <hi>Dives</hi> denied but his own, but theſe Cormorants, would <hi>Judas</hi> like carry the Purſe, ſnatch at Crown-Lands, and ſwallow Biſhopricks, but ſtarve their owners, as the Defenders of the <hi>Good Old-Cauſe</hi> did before.</p>
            <p>Concerning their unmannerly medling with the Kings Prerogative in their Votes, I will only ſay, if the King had taken advantage of the Offers, which that tranſport of joy, affection, and zeal, at his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration, would have inclined his people to make him; (for then we were as men in a dream, as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, we had ſuch ſorrowful Reſentments of our petulant encroachment on the Sovereignty, ſuch ſevere reflections on our Diſ-loyalty, that we thought though we parted with all, we could not over-do, or over-act for the Intereſt of the Monarchy, which we found by the want of it, was the beſt preſervative of our own,) there had not been room now for theſe Debates anent Prerogative and Priviledges, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and what not, which are ſo Seditiouſly ſet on foot, and managed ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapertly.</p>
            <p>I will not rake any further into the proceedings and practiſes of a ſtrong Party, in the grand Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Nation, and other Courts, I find them ſet
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99305:13"/>out to my hand very lively and juſtly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Miles Burn's</hi> Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> on <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 9.</note> by a neater Pen, who has repreſented with equal Eloquence and Ingenuity, the devices and pragmatical fetches of the Faction.</p>
            <p>I'le only mention one Vote that paſſed the Houſe, it was, that if any miſchief befell the King, be ſure the Papiſts would bear the blame of it, and undergo the puniſhment, whereby, any Phanatick Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creant might ſecurely prove Regicid, for by this he was ſure not to be queſtioned or quarrelled; poor Innocents, be't to bear the infamy of the Fact, and fall Victims to expiate the guilt of others. The <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or any ſuſpected to be ſo, were marked out to fall as Sacrifices to the cruel Saviours of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for a ſlander and ſuſpicion, was ſuffiient pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation againſt theſe or the Kings beſt friends, when great Degrees of Treaſon and Sedition in others were minced into <hi>Miſpriſion of Treaſon,</hi> little Abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and I know not what.</p>
            <p>This Vote was much like <hi>Noſtredamus</hi>'s Sons Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, who foretold the City on ſuch a day ſhould be burnt, and accordingly ſet on fire, there want not ſome who Prophecy the very miſchief they intend to perpetrate, there are who even wiſh theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, they would bear the World in hand, they deſire not to come to paſs, and by faint ſpeaking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſlily animate people to theſe Seditious Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and Treaſonable Practices, they pretend to abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate; they give Life to theſe dangerous fears, unjuſt jealouſies, and malignant diſcontents, they ſeem to harangue and remonſtrate againſt. This is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined piece of knavery the party has often uſed, even to wound the Government with ſuch ſeeming kind, but venemous, Inſinuations, and vent their malice in Charities Livery; how like this is to his Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99305:13"/>who betrayed our Saviour with a kiſs, I leave you to determine.</p>
            <p>If it be now queſtioned, whether the Popiſh, or Phanatick Party, be moſt dangerous to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? or which of theſe, was the late King, or his preſent Majeſty is in moſt hazard? To this I ſay, we all know who acted upon the Father, what was alledged others Plotted and Contrived againſt the Son; have not our King, our Nobles, our Prieſts, been dragged to Gibbets, haled to Scaffolds, made Tragical Spectacles of Ignominy and Diſ-honour, by the cruel malice of the One, while the other ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured their Lives, and waſted their Fortunes, to ſerve and ſave oppreſſed Majeſty, and ſupport the Throne, when it was tottering? Did not ſome of the <hi>Romiſh Communion</hi> cleave to the King in His ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, when, Loyalty was a Crime, and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion Triumphant, while the other tack'd about with the Times, ſtooped to proſperous Villany, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored the mock-Idol of Tyranny and Oppreſſion, of their own ſetting up. Have not State-Committies of Safety, and Kirke-Commiſſions for Reformation, bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out as cruel Edicts againſt Mens Perſons, Lives, Liberties, Offices, and Eſtates, and put them in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, with as much ſevertiy, as ever the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition? Have not Home-Conventicles, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publican-Clubs, ſent out ſparkes, to the diſturbance of the Peace, and the ſhaking of the Government, theſe ſeveral years, beyond any thing the <hi>Romiſh</hi>-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave was able to effectuate.</p>
            <p>If the one twit the Papiſts with a <hi>Jack Clement,</hi> who Murthered a King, they'l tell you of a more daring wickedneſs in <hi>Jack Presbyter,</hi> who Murthered another, but with ſome more ceremonious Sanctity, mock-Juſtice, and ſuch like ſhameleſs Circumſtances
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99305:14"/>of damned Hypocriſie:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>One of the Murderers of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of</hi> St. Andrews.</note> If you tell them of a <hi>Ravilliac,</hi> they'l anſwer, a <hi>Rathillat</hi> no more reſembles the Name, than tranſcribed the Villany. And now ſhall we think the <hi>Principles</hi> of Depoſing <hi>Kings</hi> more Savoury in the Mouths of <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> than in ſome <hi>Popiſh-School-men?</hi> Shall we think the practice of <hi>King-killing</hi> and <hi>Aſſaſſinating Biſhops,</hi> when it is for <hi>Religion,</hi> more Hallowed in <hi>Schiſmatical Butchers,</hi> than in ſome <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Miſcreants?</hi> Yet the Actors of theſe <hi>Barbarities,</hi> are the Chariots and Horſemen of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the <hi>Patrons</hi> of <hi>Gods Cauſe,</hi> the <hi>Precious ones of the Lord,</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs</hi> of the <hi>Faction:</hi> But if theſe be the Prime Candidates of Heaven; then <hi>Shimei</hi> and <hi>Rabſhakeh, Corah</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> and all the men of <hi>Belial</hi> need not queſtion <hi>Aſſurance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>Faction</hi> think not themſelves ſecure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Covenant;</hi> they had experience of the Service<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of this to their Helliſh Purpoſes: This was the <hi>Gideon Sword,</hi> with which they Threſh'd the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> and Sequeſter'd the <hi>Church,</hi> cut off the <hi>Crown,</hi> and threw down the <hi>Mytre:</hi> But they knew the Name was odious, and the Court would ſcent the Deſign, that well-meaning People would ſtartle at the mention of a Word ſo Fatal to the <hi>Nations;</hi> as we cannot ſee the very Inſtruments wherewith our Friends are Butcher'd; and there is ſomthing I know not what in the Names of venemous Creatures, that grate our Ears, fret our Blood, and touch us with a ſecret Horror, ſo the Word <hi>Covenant</hi> would Alarm the Loyal of the Land, it muſt be ſmoothed and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for theſe <hi>Oſtrich-ſtomachs,</hi> tender of any thing but Monſtrous Villanies, for theſe delicate Ears only erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Seditious News, into an <hi>Aſſociation:</hi> But as Pyrats change their Flag, but not their Purpoſe; High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way-men their Habit, but not their Practice; Beaſts
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99305:14"/>of Prey their Habitations, but not their Savage Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; ſo Rebels, retain their Bloody Deſigns under all Diſguiſes: And as their <hi>Arch-leader Cromwel</hi> would not be call'd <hi>King,</hi> that he might act the Tyrant, and play the Deſtroyer in a <hi>Protectors</hi> habit; ſo the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> muſt be Antiquated, and an <hi>Aſſociation</hi> ſubſtituted in its room; and theſe are as like one another, as <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Iſcariot,</hi> as Convertible as <hi>Cromwel</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was truly ſtrange, that after all our dear bought Experience, after the Bleſſings of the Reſtoration of the <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and our own Reſtitution to our Rights and Liberties thereby; after all the Diſcoveries of the Party, which a little glance backward might give people; any ſhould have been deluded twice in one Age, by the very ſame Stratagems: There is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain faſcination in Sedition, when it can ſo ſucceſsful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly erect its Trophies on Peoples Credulity, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch a Nation twice in one Age by the ſelf-ſame Methods.</p>
            <p>All Grand Conſpiracies againſt the Government are carried on under a <hi>Sham-zeal</hi> for <hi>Religion,</hi> a <hi>Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit Affection</hi> to the <hi>Publick,</hi> a <hi>Crocodile Pity</hi> for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed <hi>Liberty,</hi> an earneſt deſire to <hi>Redreſs Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and when theſe are managed with a <hi>Stentorian Voice,</hi> and <hi>Senatorian Gravity,</hi> with <hi>Shaftsburian Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangues,</hi> and <hi>Cromwelian Devotions,</hi> with <hi>Long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Preachments,</hi> and <hi>Aſſembly Faſts,</hi> with <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed Curſes,</hi> and <hi>Miſapply'd Texts;</hi> with an <hi>O Yes, O Yes,</hi> the <hi>Cauſe of God,</hi> the <hi>Cauſe of God,</hi> and the other circumſtances of Pageantry, which were tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to rehearſe; down muſt all go without pity, and the <hi>Work</hi> goes bravely on, though the <hi>King</hi> be Butcher'd, <hi>Religion</hi> Deſtroy'd, under pretence of Defending of it it, Property fall Victim to the keeneſt or longeſt Sword, and <hi>Arbitrarineſs</hi> Introduced under a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfit Flag of ſtaving it off.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:99305:15"/>
            <p>When the ſame <hi>Antimonarchical</hi> Principles <hi>Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies</hi> and <hi>Pretences,</hi> (the Blinds under which Treaſon and Murder made their advance formerly) are now ſet on foot, though ſome of the Actors be changed, the ſame fatal Game is certainly intended to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted in the Nation: This is not the Fanciful <hi>Idea</hi> of a Cloyſter'd <hi>Monk,</hi> or the Chymerical fear of a Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly man; this is not the contemplative Notion of a ſarcaſtical Wit, this is not a remote poſſibility, or uncertain contingency, but what we have heard with our Ears, ſaw with our Eyes, felt on our Backs, and known to our Coſt.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Sedition</hi> produces not all its ill Effects at once, but mends its pace by degrees, till it burſt out in Thunder and drop Blood; thus impudently (after theſe ſeveral ſteps) it ſhews it bare face in a formidable <hi>Rebellion, Private Whiſpers, Licentious Invectives, Secret Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, Pragmatical Medlings, Preſumptuous En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments, Factious Bandyings</hi> uſher'd an open <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion</hi> in both Kingdoms. I will not interrupt the Joy of this day, by grating your Ears with recounting the diſmal Conſequences had iſſued upon the ſucceſs of this <hi>Rebellion;</hi> if Providence had permitted ſo far the puniſhment of our Sins: Nor will I expatiate in aggravating the Injuſtice of the Attempt, or the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious Ingratitude and Treachery of the Actors; the Skars we yet retain of our late unhappy Troubles (which the ſignal Advantages of the Reſtitution of the Government, the Clemency of the late King, and the Conduct of our preſent Sovereign, (who then bore a great part of the Care without the Crown) have much worn off) are no ſadder Indications of what is paſt, than Prognoſticks of the Calamitous events we had groaned under, if the <hi>Rebellion</hi> had proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd: And that will eaſily appear, if you conſider theſe two particulars.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:99305:15"/>
            <p n="1">1. The reſpite the Loyal of the Land had by the Bleſſings of the Reſtoration, has ſet the Teeth of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels on edge, who like Tygers and Woolves, and ſuch Savage Creatures, have their edge whetted by being with-held ſo long from their Prey: And God knows, if they ſhould Triumph over our Liberties and Tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple our Honour in the Duſt a ſecond time, by a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous <hi>Rebellion,</hi> without any Metaphore, our latter end would have been worſe than the beginning: O what Cruel Impoſers on the Conſciences of others? What Violent Invaders of Property? What Inſolent Oppreſſions of our Freedom, have they formerly proved, by which we may rationally conjecture, as they are improved in Cunning and Impudence for carrying on the ſame Villainous Methods, there cruelty were no leſs, if put in the ſame circumſtances of Power and Opportunity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As their Malice was increas'd, ſo was their Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy, and <hi>Rebellion</hi> never marches more furiouſly, or Haraſſes more cruelly, than when it ſtrikes and Fights in the <hi>Name of the Lord;</hi> when it comes with a <hi>Curſe ye</hi> Meroz <hi>becauſe they came not to help the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the mighty; And Curſed be he that doth the Work of the Lord negligently, or keepeth back his Sword from Blood:</hi> A Religious Rebel, a Seditious Saint, a Gifted Brother, a Godly <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> with the <hi>Bible</hi> in one Hand, and a <hi>Dagger</hi> in the other; with the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt in his Mouth, and Spite againſt the King in his Heart, will exceed a <hi>Jew</hi> in Obſtinacy, a <hi>Turk</hi> in Cruelty; yea, out do an <hi>Indian</hi> in Barbarity.</p>
            <p>Thus I have drawn a Scheme of the Actings of the Party, unfolded their Windings, diffected their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice, by which they ſought to Dethrone the King that lately was, and Exclude His preſent Majeſty, in whoſe Exaltation to, and Preſervation on the Throne,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99305:16"/>in deſpite of all the Machinations of the Faction, God has ſignally vindicated his Providence, and manifeſted his Care of Crown'd Heads: That now like a trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Conquerour in a Holy Boaſt, he may ſay, <hi>Why did the Faction rage, and the People imagine a vain thing?</hi> Why did Grandees Combine? And Rulers take Councel together? For all their Oppoſition, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King,</hi> &amp;c. And we may ſay, <hi>He that ſitteth in Heaven hath Laugh'd; the Lord has had them in Deriſion, he hath ſpoken to them in his Wrath, and vex'd them in his ſore diſpleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We now ſee God ſuffers Rebellious Contrivances to go on to ſome pitch of Maturity, and make ſome Progreſs, as the gradual ſteps of Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the reſtleſs <hi>Faction</hi> made; but it is for the further Confuſion of the Actors, and the Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his own Glory, in their more ſignal overthrow: For if ſuch Courſes were nipped in the Bud, or made too ſoon Abortive; it would bring leſs Shame to the Authors, leſs Terrour to others, fewer Admirers of his Providence, or Reverers of his Juſtice: And this is a ſignal indication of God's peculiar In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in our King, and ſpecial Care over him: That when the Party had cloſely and cunningly laid their Projects in their Clandeſtine Cabals, and brought them to the point of Execution, <hi>He diſappointed their Devices,
<note place="margin">Job. 5.12.13.</note> that their Hands could not perform their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes; He took the Wiſe in their own Craftineſs and precipitated their Counſel: Yet have I ſet my King upon my Holy Hill of</hi> Zion.</p>
            <p>As God rejoyces in bafling the Attempts, detecting the Cheats, confounding the Policies, and Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the oppoſition of His and the King's Foes, here, <hi>Yet have I,</hi> &amp;c. So, let us in ſuch miraculous trains of Providence, whereby the Plots and Power of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99305:16"/>King's Enemies are defeat; let us Glory and Boaſt in the Name of the Lord, <hi>Who giveth Salvation unto Kings,</hi> and ſtilleth the Tumults of the People: Let us Triumph in ſuch events of his Providence, as ſeal particular care of the King, his Affection to his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, his concernedneſs for his Intereſt; with whoſe Preſervation the Security of our Laws, the freedom of our Religion, the Honour of our Nation is twiſted. Let us ſay with <hi>Ahimaaz,
<note place="margin">2 Sam 18.28.</note> Bleſſed be the Lord which hath deliver'd up the men, that lift up their Hand againſt my Lord, the King: Now know we, that the Lord ſaveth his Anointed; he will hear him from his Holy Heaven; By the ſtrength of his Right hand he hath wrought Salvation for us: Some truſt in Chariots,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 20.</note> and ſome in Horſes: But we will remember the Name of the Lord our God: They are brought down and fallen that roſe up againſt us: But we are riſen and ſtand upright.</hi> Behold, as Aged Men are reviv'd with a preſent ſolace at the ſucceſsful Encounters, and maſter'd Misfortunes, of their Youth: Or Travellers raviſh'd in their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, with rehearſal of their toilſome Pilgrimage; ſo may we rejoyce in conſideration of the myſterious Conduct of Divine Providence, by which our King and the Nations have eſcap'd.</p>
            <p>From the Conduct of Divine Providence in Settling our King on the Throne of his Anceſtors, maugre all the oppoſition to the contrary: Let no cunning <hi>Achitophel</hi> flatter himſelf in his cloſe-laid Deſigns; or Treacherous <hi>Abſalom</hi> pride himſelf in his Power or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularity: We ſee God either fruſtrates their Devices,
<note place="margin">Job. 5.12.</note> or weakens their ſtrength, that they cannot accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh them, or enſnares them in their own Craft, or precipitates their Counſels to their own undoing. The Policy of Man is too ſhallow to grapple with Infinite Wiſdom; and his Power too weak to oppoſe Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99305:17"/>God beats men often with their own Weapons, and turns their Stratagems againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their ruine, plays his Game by their Hand, when they leaſt intend it; cauſeth their Policy to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teract it ſelf, in accompliſhing what it was deſign'd to baffle, as in the caſe of <hi>Joſeph, Moſes, Jonah,</hi> and our Sovereign; we may transfer to the fraudulent practices of the Enemies of the King, what <hi>Jethro</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> in the thing they dealed proudly, God is above them; in the thing they dealed treacherouſly, God was above them: <hi>Yet have I ſet my King,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Let theſe who took encouragement to perſiſt in their Villanies from the ſucceſs of their <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and aſpers'd Providence upon this ſcore, as approving their Treaſons, like that <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> who, upon his fair gale, after he plunder'd the Temple, cry'd out, <hi>O behold, how God loves Sacriledge:</hi> Let them now behold, how God vindicates himſelf; and daſhes their confidence, in detecting their Plots, and baffling their Attempts, in infatuating their Councel, and cruſhing their Power; and now quit all Enterpriſes againſt that, which God ſo ſignally in the iſſues of his Providence takes under his Patrociny and favourable Protection: Let them now ſee their Argument turned againſt themſelves; we ſee the Chaſe is quite turn'd: And though Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſuffer Treaſon and Rebellion to vapour it for a time, and bear all like a torrent before them: Yet ſhe will not proſtitute her ſelf to befriend them ſtill, ſhe will not be violent'd long to favour <hi>Rebellion</hi> with ſucceſs, or crown Treaſons with Triumphs: God hath more than ſufficiently vindicated his permiſſive Providence in winking at the Indignities done <hi>Charles</hi> the I. by his ſpecial care of his Poſterity, in preſerving them in their Exile; in returning them with ſuch uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Acclamations, in advancing two of them peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99305:17"/>to the Throne of their Anceſtors, for all the <hi>Plots</hi> of their Foes, the policies of their Heads, the malice of their Hearts, or oppoſition of their Hands; And next the Miracle of the Reſtoration of <hi>Charles</hi> the II. The advancement of our preſent Gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign to His Throne, through ſo many Difficulties, Intricacies and Obſtacles, is matter of aſtoniſhment to all conſidering Perſons; and ſpeaks out a Chain of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Providence that encircles Kings: We may ſay,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.23.</note> 
               <hi>It is the Lord's doing, and is marvellous in our Eyes; we will rejoyce and be glad for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conſideration of the Myſterious tract of the Divine Providence in behalf of the King, in maſtering all the Lets, and conquering the hinderances of his juſt and deſerved Exaltation to his <hi>Throne,</hi> may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Him and Us to truſt the Divine Goodneſs for His Majeſties future Proſperity: Theſe Oppoſitions in the Morning of his Reign, were but miſts, through which he has broken Victoriouſly with Splendor: And we may rationally hope the reſt of his days will be more Serene, and his End, like the <hi>Sun</hi>'s Declenſion, in a beautiful Cloud: We need not fear his future Peaceful <hi>Reign; Seditions, Conſpiraties,</hi> when they are <hi>detected, Popular Tumults,</hi> when they are <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, Inteſtine Inſurrections,</hi> when they are <hi>cruſh'd, Sham-Plots</hi> and <hi>Sancy Competitions,</hi> when they are <hi>baſted,</hi> are the Security of the <hi>Throne,</hi> and the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the <hi>Government:</hi> Theſe are like Winds, which ſhake and threaten to pluck up Trees, yet ſtrengthen their rooting; or like theſe morning Clouds which Eclipſe the <hi>Sun,</hi> or darken the <hi>Air,</hi> but leave the one more ſprightly, and the other more clear: That Chain of Providence which preſerv'd him in his Exile, where the diſaſter of his Fortune did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Gallantry of his Spirit, (as uſually falls out
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99305:18"/>in perſons of an Ordinary Elevation) but it broke forth in his Military Encounters, to the Conqueſt of his Enemies, and the aſtoniſhment of his Beholders, and wonderfully reſtor'd Him and his Sacred Brother to their undoubted Rights, will not deſert Him: Theſe former inſtances are Enſurances to Us; He is God's darling, and the Object of his ſpecial Care, happy Preſages of the ſame Providence, watchful Eye and tender regard of him ſtill; We may allude to what <hi>David</hi> ſays,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.37.</note> 
               <hi>He that deliver'd him from the paw of the Lyon, and out of the paw of the Bear, will not leave him in the hand of the</hi> Philiſtines:
<note place="margin">2 Chr. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>He that hath deliver'd him, and doth deliver him,</hi> will make his Days Many, His Reign Proſperous, His Enemies <hi>As ſtraw trodden down for the Dunghil,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 25.10.</note> His Subjects Happy, His Crown Flouriſhing, and his Armies Victorious.</p>
            <p>And it cannot be doubted but it will be ſo, if we anſwer the Deſign of Providence, and our Duty in Loyalty and Obedience; we ſhould convince the World, that though the King be of a different Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion from us, yet Loyalty towards Him is an eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Ingredient of ours: Let us labour to exceed <hi>Papiſts</hi> in Affection to his Perſon, Obedience to his Laws, and Concernedneſs for the Safety of his Crown, and the Happineſs of his Reign, that we may vindicate our ſelves and our Religion from the unjuſt Aſperſions of any Adverſary: So the King, like a Loving Father, will make no diſcrimination, in the diſtribution of his Favour and Protection, for the different Features of his Children: We ſee this, and thank the King for it already; and we need not jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous the continuance of it, ſo long as we perſevere in our Duty: Nothing can make us unhappy under his Government, or obſtruct from us the benign In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of the <hi>Throne,</hi> but our own ungovernable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99305:18"/>Let us, by all Offices of Humanity and Charity, treat our Fellow Subjects without diſtinction, ſince we all Worſhip one God, and ſerve one King, and hope to meet all in one Heaven: Let us forbear bitter Railing and Reviling, for there may be more of a helliſh Spirit in that, than there is of <hi>Antichriſtianiſm</hi> in ſome objects of our Rage: And ſince our Hearts and Affections, our Prayers and Devotion meet in one Center, as to the Kings Welfare and Happineſs; let this unite us in Love and Peaceableneſs together; let our conteſt be, which ſhall exceed one another in Loyalty and Humanity; not like the Briar and the Thiſtle, which ſhall rankle one another moſt, or fret our Superiors; but let it be, like that betwixt the Vine and the Olive, which ſhall be moſt beneficial; like that of <hi>Ariſtides</hi> to <hi>Themiſtocles,
<note place="margin">Plutarch <hi>vita The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt.</hi>
                  </note> Laying aſide pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Piques, let us ſtudy which of us can be moſt Service<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to our Country, moſt Dutiful to our Sovereign, and helpful to one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to rivet this Loyalty in your Hearts, let me offer ſome Conſiderations from Nature, from Reaſon, from Religion, and Intereſt. <hi>Firſt,</hi> what <hi>Curtius</hi> obſerves,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ingenita qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſdam gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus erga re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſuos vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio.</hi> Curti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> 
               <hi>That ſome Climats and Nations are naturally more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to revere and affect their Kings, than others,</hi> is true of the Body of our Nation: And of all People under Heaven, We are under the greateſt Obligation to our Monarchy, and to aſſert the Kings Right; for two thouſand years we knew no other Government, and the Reins were held in a Lineal Succeſſion by the Fore-fathers of his Sacred Majeſty, who now Happily ſways the Scepters over us: The <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Nation has been fam'd all the World over for its Loyalty and Courage; this was the <hi>Genius</hi> and Complexion of our Country, until our late unhappy Times; a <hi>Scots</hi> Traytor was of Old as contradictory, as a Drunken
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99305:19"/>
               <hi>Christian,</hi> or an Innocent Robber: And it had been ſo ſtill, if a new <hi>Sect</hi> or <hi>Hotch-Potch</hi> Party had not ſprung up here, and in our Neighbour Kingdom; who could reconcile Godlineſs and Villainy, Sacriledge and Saintſhip, Religion and Rebellion; great preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Strictneſs, but affectors of Looſeneſs; of ſtrong Faith, but little Charity; of great Devotion, but little Honeſty; of ſpecious Names, but vitious Natures; of fair Pretences, but foul and abominable Practices: Theſe, theſe, were they that debauch'd the Nation from its Integrity, and deprav'd ſome People with Diſloyalty; God grant, we may recover our Antient Reputation, and repair the Credit of our Country, by a ſtedfaſt Adherence to the Crown;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nunquam libertas gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior extat quam ſub re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>epto.</hi> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>audia.</note> and make ſome Compenſation for the Indignities done the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> the Diſſervice done the <hi>Son,</hi> the Ingratitude done the <hi>Duke,</hi> by a Dutiful Allegiance to the King.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We have the greateſt reaſon in the World to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage us to perſevere in Loyalty;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In regno naei ſumus ubi parere eſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertas.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca.</note> We live under a Monarchy that is the beſt temper'd in the World, our Liberty and Happineſs depends on our Obedience; and theſe are ſo twiſted with the Sovereignity, that they ſtand or fall, live and dye together: We have a King, whoſe tender years have not been corrupted with Luxury, but one who bore the yoak in his youth, and hath been early diſciplin'd to Hardſhip, in whom there is nothing of Softneſs or Effeminacy to encourage the moſt daring Rebel: We have a King, who is no Novice to the Intrigues of State or Mines of Policy, one that will not be impos'd on by the Craft of any <hi>Achitophel;</hi> one who is habituated to the difficulties of Government, whoſe Vigilance eaſed the Care, whoſe Policy proſper'd the Reign, of his Royal Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whoſe Sagacity detected afar off the Rebellious Deſigns of a Monſtrous teeming <hi>Faction</hi> then, whoſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99305:19"/>Courage and Reſolution daſh'd their Impudence, and cruſh'd their Inſolence ſince: We live under a King, whoſe Stoutneſs and Conduct, whoſe Valour and Gallantry, has made him the Terror of his Foes, the Envy of his Neighbours, and the Darling of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. The Benignity of the Kings Temper, the Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of his Nature, the Gentleneſs of his Reign, (which perhaps is beyond parallel; that for the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion</hi> lately commenced, none fell in this Capital City, the ſeat of Publick Juſtice, but two, by the Hand of the common Executioner) the firmneſs of his Word, which he ſignaliz'd to the exaſperating of a daring <hi>Faction;</hi> theſe, with the conſtellation of the other Royal Virtues which adorn his great Soul, are Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of more Proſperity to thoſe Nations from his Government, (though he differ from us in Points of Faith and Matters of Worſhip) than could be expected from a <hi>Spurious Competitor,</hi> or a <hi>Proteſtant <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper:</hi> And when I have ſaid ſo, I have wrong'd none by the Compariſon but the <hi>King,</hi> and I am at his <hi>Mercy</hi> for it: But ſtill I'll aſſert, we have all the Reaſon imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to maintain his undoubted Title with our Lives and Fortunes, againſt all the <hi>Proteſtant Rebels</hi> in the World: And that becauſe,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Our <hi>Religion</hi> tyes us thereto, <hi>Loyalty</hi> is the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Truly <hi>Proteſtant Religion:</hi> And theſe who act otherwiſe, have its Form, but not its Power, and treat it no otherwiſe, than <hi>Joah</hi> did <hi>Amaſa,</hi> under colour of affection to its Name, wound it under the fifth rib. No Religion in the World, no Syſtem of Divinity, no platform of Morality, no model of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, which the Sages of <hi>Greece,</hi> or the Senators of <hi>Rome</hi> ever invented, preſs'd Loyalty from ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Topicks, or rational Arguments, as our <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion:</hi> Our Duty to the King ſtands on the ſame Baſis
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99305:20"/>in our Religion, with our Duty to God; its perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance encourag'd with the ſame Eternal Reward, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veted with the ſame weighty Conſiderations, its omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or neglect attended with the ſame Penalties and Dangers, that are entail'd on contempt of God, or the greateſt wickedneſs: Our Religion is no more poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive againſt <hi>Whoredom</hi> and <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> than it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Rebellion:</hi> And among us a <hi>Rebel</hi> againſt the King, under whatſoever pretence, is no more an Unnatural <hi>Scot</hi> than a Hypocritical <hi>Proteſtant:</hi> And ſo long as we Live and Act according to the Principles of our Religion, our Zeal for that will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make us <hi>Factious</hi> or <hi>Seditious:</hi> And the King will be encourag'd to protect us in the Exerciſe of it. Therefore,</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Intereſt,</hi> which in this Selfiſh Age preponderates all other Conſiderations, ſhould have a mighty influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on Loyalty and Peaceableneſs; <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty,</hi> the Darlings of Mankind, the <hi>Hue</hi> and <hi>Cry</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> are never in hazard; but when the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignity is invaded, and <hi>Prerogative</hi> impair'd: We rebelled our ſelves into <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Slavery,</hi> into <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion, Arbitrarineſs</hi> and <hi>Irreligion:</hi> He, that would comfortably enjoy the Fruit of his own Vine, and ſit with Eaſe under his own Fig-tree, can do it moſt contentedly, when the King, like the <hi>Sun</hi> in a ſerene day, diffuſes his warm and kindly Beams without diſturbance: Our <hi>Liberty</hi> conſiſts in our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, our Submiſſion to our Sovereign's Will is the riſe of our Felicity: Theſe, who ſeek to better their Eſtate by <hi>Sedition,</hi> are often undone by their <hi>Rebellion:</hi> We have bleeding Inſtances of theſe, who have fallen from their <hi>Legitimate Grandeur,</hi> by affecting and aſpiring after unjuſt Greatneſs.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99305:20"/>
            <p>For Concluſion, let me add theſe three Directions, which may be helpful to preſerve us in <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the King; and they are patly adjuſted to what I have already ſaid, and to our Circumſtances.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us not entertain in our minds Diſcontent at the publick Adminiſtration of Affairs; <hi>It is out of the abundance of the Heart the Mouth ſpeaketh, the Hand acteth;</hi> if our Hearts be ſeaſon'd with Affection to the King: Neither <hi>Murmurs</hi> nor <hi>Invectives</hi> will find matter within us to work on; People may be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aw'd from <hi>Seditions Speeches</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of the Law, and the Watchfulneſs of Rulers: But if Diſcontent be harbour'd in our Spirits, it will break out on the firſt opportunity: The more wary we are this way, the Government is more Safe, and we the more Happy; People that reſolve within them prejudice againſt their Rulers, are driven to ſhoot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their Mark, and commit Out-rages they never dream'd, nor thought poſſible for them once to have fallen into: I believe <hi>Judas</hi> never intended to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence <hi>Traytor,</hi> when he began to play the <hi>Thief,</hi> nor did his Followers purpoſe to bring the King to a Scaffold, when they firſt indulged themſelves in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligning</hi> his Government, and <hi>Aſperſing</hi> his Perſon; but in no Sin more than in <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Treaſon: They muſt needs run whom the Devil drives;</hi> Beware then of Diſcontent, the very firſt <hi>Seeds</hi> of <hi>Miſchief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us never be Impos'd upon by the ſame <hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems,</hi> by which we were formerly deluded; the <hi>Clamorous Harangues</hi> of ſome <hi>Factious Demagogues</hi> againſt <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Government;</hi> which were never felt till the <hi>King</hi> was dethron'd and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion</hi> Proſperous: The great <hi>Darlings</hi> of the <hi>Populacy,</hi> are <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Property;</hi> and theſe cunning Men that ride it as they pleaſe, make Zeal for theſe, a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verture</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:99305:21"/>for their <hi>Covetous Projects</hi> and <hi>Ambitious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns:</hi> And People are ſo eaſily tickl'd with the Beauty of the Pretence, that they are precipitated or e're they are aware into diſmal Courſes, deſtructive in the Iſſue to both: So that they are made to truckle under their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> who pretended the greateſt affection to their <hi>Liberty,</hi> and vapour it with the property of the Subject, and the <hi>Sacrilegious Spoils</hi> of the <hi>Church: Tyranny</hi> is a Child of the Croud; and never any have more furiouſly Spur-gall'd that great Beaſt, than thoſe who have crouch'd and faun'd to cajole it; and when it is wheedled out of its Wit and Intereſt, as well as out of its Submiſſion and Obedience; there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſet up like <hi>Maſſinello</hi> in <hi>Naples;</hi> ſomething, as a Judicious and Loyal Author has it, <hi>That is a King Incognito,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nalſon's <hi>common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ereſt</hi> cap. 4.</note> or in <hi>Diſguiſe,</hi> or a <hi>Tyrant</hi> in the Dreſs of a private Man; though he were call'd, <hi>The Protector of the Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Satan</hi> is never more to be dreaded, than when he transforms himſelf into an Angel of Light; and is never more a <hi>Devil,</hi> than when he appears a <hi>Saint:</hi> So the Enemies of the Government are never more to be ſuſpect, than when they ſpeak much good of <hi>God,</hi> and ill of the <hi>King;</hi> and think their Zeal for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, a Paſs-port for Injuries done the Later; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as God in his Word, makes Obedience to our <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours,</hi> the <hi>Test</hi> of our Dutifulneſs to himſelf: Do not think, after our dear-bought Experience of the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy of the Party, that their ſpecious Pretences for <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> will juſtify, yea or extenuate our ſordid complyance, for all our good meaning.</p>
            <p>There is not the leaſt queſtion, but as in <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s unnatural <hi>Rebellion,</hi> ſome in the ſimplicity of their Heart went with the Drove; ſo in our late Wars, many well-meaning perſons were cheated out of their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99305:21"/>Duty and Loyalty, who came too late to their Wits, the juſt conviction of their Folly, or a due ſenſe of their Sin, when they found they were deceiv'd; their honeſt Meaning miſ-improven, their Help miſ-apply'd, even to the ruin of what they intended to maintain and promote: Yet what the better was the King of their Honeſt Intentions or Loyal Affections, when they were active Inſtruments of bringing about the Miſchiefs, under which He and the Kingdoms were Oppreſs'd: Their Honeſt Meaning might extenuate their Fault, and blunt the edge of their ſelf-ſtinging Reflections, and put them in probable capacity of God's Mercy and the King's Clemency; becauſe they might ſay with the <hi>Apoſtle, They did it in Ignorance;</hi> But in the Iſſue there was no difference, <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King, Religion</hi> and the <hi>Government, Liberty</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty,</hi> ſuffer'd by the Zealous miſtakes of the deluded <hi>Innocents,</hi> as well as by the furious practices of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning Incendiaries:</hi> Nay, the more really Honeſt ſome were, who were ſtollen off their Feet, the more Pernicious was their Errour in Debauching others from their Duty; the more influential their example to the detriment of the King, and the ruin of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Let us reflect on the <hi>Tragical Cataſtrophe,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal end of <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Rebellion;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſilia cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lida &amp; inho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſta prima fronte feſta, tractatu du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, eventu triſtia.</hi> Liv. <hi>lib.</hi> 31.</note> ſeditious Attempts and Deſigns, how pleaſing ſoever they ſeem to be in the beginning; how promiſing and flattering ſoever they appear in their firſt Aſpect, yet in the Progreſs they prove dangerous, and in the Iſſue fatal. The fond hopes of aſpiring Spirits, by which they build Caſtles in the Air, flatters them to their undoing, like ſome Serpents, which tickle and wound at once; and that which in the Project promiſes them a great reward and advantage, is in the Iſſue full of danger
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99305:22"/>and difaſter: The fair Deſigns of <hi>Traytors,</hi> are but the haught and painted Images of a deceitful Dream, inſtead of which they meet with an inglorious End. Many Inſtances from divine and human Stories could be adduc'd of this kind; ambitious Men, who leap to Greatneſs too ſoon, repent their Madneſs too late, and often Hopp without Heads; but few read their own Deſtiny in ſuch ſad Preſidents as are on Record, or look upon ſuch fatal Examples as their own Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, though few or no Sins bear greater <hi>Stigmas</hi> of Divine Vengeance, or marks of Human Juſtice than <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Rebellion;</hi> the Fomenters or Promoters of ſuch Villainies are ſcorch'd with the <hi>Flames</hi> of their own kindling: And were there no more to caution us againſt ſuch Practices, than the tender conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Families, who would embarke with a <hi>Factious</hi> Party, if it were no more but for this, that the Dowry and Inheritance he leaves his Wife and Children, are Poverty and Infamy; and though the Clemency of the King forgive the Guilt, yet this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves not the Ignominy. Well! let me ſhut up all with <hi>Solomon</hi>'s advice, <hi>Fear God and Honour the King, and meddle not with thoſe that are given to Change:
<note place="margin">Prov. 24.21, 22.</note> For their Calamity ſhall ariſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the ruin of them both.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
